A Guide to the Records of the Virginia State Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services Board, 1903-1996
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
A Guide to the Records of the Virginia State Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services Board, 1903-1996
The Library of Virginia
42741
14.5 cu. ft. (24 boxes)
Virginia. State Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services Board
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The Virginia Freedom of Information Act (Code of Virginia, 2.2-3705.5) and the Virginia Health Records Privacy Act (Code of Virginia, 32.1-172.1:03) establish guidelines for restricting access to medical and other confidential forms of information in order to protect personal privacy. Protected health information (PHI) as defined under the Privacy Regulations issued under the Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act (HIPAA) includes, but is not limited to, personally identifiable information such as names, addresses, and social security numbers. The Virginia Public Records Act (Code of Virginia, 42.1-78) includes a provision for closing all privacy protected information for 75 years from the date of creation. In accordance with this legislation, the Library of Virginia can and will restrict, in whole or in part, access to any privacy protected medical information or any other confidential information contained in these records.
Privacy protected information will be sealed or redacted upon request of the material, and the records may be available for research in their altered form. When redaction is deemed implausible by library staff due to the type, size, or condition of the records, the records will be completely closed. All records more than 75 years old are open for research.
Acquisition Information
Transferred by the Virginia Dept. of Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services, 100 Bank St., Richmond, Virginia, 10 July 2006.
Historical Information
The Dept. of Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services traces its beginnings to the first institution in the New World designed for the treatment of the mentally ill, which opened in Williamsburg in 1773. Now known as Eastern State Hospital, it was followed by Western State Hospital, in Staunton (1828), Central State Hospital, in Petersburg (1870), and Southwestern State Hospital, in Marion (1887). Other instutions under the control of this department are: Catawba Hospital, opened in 1908; Central Virginia Training Center, Lynchburg, opened in 1911; DeJarnette Center, Staunton, opened in 1932; Northern Virginia Mental Health Institute, Falls Church, opened in 1968; Northern Virginia Training Center, Fairfax, opened in 1973; Piedmont Geriatric Hospital, Burkeville, opened in 1967; Southeastern Virginia Training Center, Chesapeake, opened in 1975; Southern Virginia Mental Health Institute, Danville, opened in 1977; Southside Virginia Training Center, Petersburg, opened in 1960; Southwestern Virginia Training Center, Hillsville, opened in 1976; and the Virginia Treatment Center for Children, Richmond, opened in 1962.
On April 3, 1942, the General Assembly passed an act establishing the Department of Mental Hygiene and Hospitals. The name of the department was changed to the Department of Mental Health and Mental Retardation by the General Assembly on March 20, 1973. It became the Department of Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services in 1987. The Department is responsible for providing a comprehensive system of services that is responsive to the mental health, mental retardation, drug abuse and alcohol dependency needs of the citizens of the Commonwealth. The Department has developed many programs to fulfill its responsibilities, including treatment, counseling, hospitalization, and rehabilitation services.
Organizationally, the department is under the Secretary of Health and Human Services. At the head of the department is a commissioner who serves at the pleasure of the governor. He or she receives overall policy and direction and guidance from the Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Board. Prior to 1903, each state hospital had its own Board of Directors which dealt directly with the General Assembly. In 1903, the individual Boards of Directors were each replaced by a three-person group called the Special Board of Directors. The Special Boards of each hospital (and beginning in 1910, the Epileptic Colony as well) answered to the newly-created General Board of Directors of State Hospitals. The General Board connected all of the state-run mental health institutions for the first time. In 1937 the individual Special Boards were abolished, and the General Board was renamed the State Hospital Board. This board consisted of seven members who were responsible for the management of all the state-run hospitals. This board was required to meet at least once each year at each hospital. In later years, the Board met on a monthly or twice-monthly basis. The State Hospital Board became the State Mental Health and Mental Retardation Board in 1973, and then the State Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services Board in 1987.
Scope and Content
Contains meeting minutes, chronological files, department publications, manuals and investigative reports that document the activities of the Virginia Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services Board and the many institutions under the heading of the Virginia Department of Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Minutes, State Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services Board, 1903-1996
Series II. Minutes, Special Board of Directors of the State Colony for Epileptics and Feebleminded, 1910-1937
Series III. Minutes, Miscellaneous Organizations, 1915-1922
Series IV. Chronological Files, 1981-1994
Series V. Mental Hygiene Surveys, 1938-1947
Series VI. Reports and Manuals, 1943-1972
Contents List
- Series I. Minutes, State Mental Health Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services Board, 1903-1996. (Box 1-5, 9-20.)
  Restricted: Meeting minutes containing patient names and information that are less than 75 years old. These records may require review by an archivist and/or redaction (if it is possible) before they are served. Contains minutes of the regular and executive sessions of the meetings of the State Mental Health Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services Board, as well as its earlier incarnations. Also included in this series are indices to the minutes and minutes from various Board committees.
  - Subseries A. Minutes, Regular Sessions, 1903-1996. (Box 1-4, 9-18.)
    Contains the minutes of the regular session meetings of the State Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services Board. The earliest minutes are handwritten and the later minutes are typed. Some of the minutes exist in two forms, bound and loose. The bound minutes are in straight chronological order, but many of the loose and more recent minutes are arranged in reverse chronological order. The minutes pertain to all of the state hospitals and institutions under the heading of the Department of Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Susbtance Abuse Services. The minutes give insight into the decision-making processes and governance of Virginia's mental health institutions, as well as budgetary matters and a variety of patient care issues.
    Arranged with bound minutes first and loose minutes second, and then chronologically within.
    - Bound Minutes.
      - April 1903-February 1913. (Box 1)
      - May 1913-August 1918. (Box 1)
      - February 1919-June 1925. (Box 1)
      - August 1925-May 1937. (Box 1)
      - Regular and Executive Sessions (Reorganized), July 1937 - June 1939. (Box 1)
      - July 1939-June 1940. (Box 1)
      - July 1940-June 1941. (Box 1)
      - July 1941-June 1942. (Box 1)
      - July 1942-June 1943. (Box 1)
      - July 1943-June 1944. (Box 1)
      - July 1944-June 1945. (Box 1)
      - July 1945-June 1946. (Box 1)
      - July 1946-June 1947. (Box 2)
      - July 1947-June 1948. (Box 2)
      - July 1948-June 1949. (Box 2)
      - July 1949-June 1950. (Box 2)
      - July 1950-June 1951. (Box 2)
      - July 1951-June 1952. (Box 2)
      - July 1952-June 1953. (Box 2)
      - July 1953-June 1954. (Box 2)
      - July 1954-June 1955. (Box 2)
      - July 1955-June 1956. (Box 2)
      - July 1956-June 1957. (Box 2)
      - July 1957-June 1958. (Box 2)
      - July 1958-June 1959. (Box 2)
      - July 1959-June 1960. (Box 3)
      - July 1960-June 1961. (Box 3)
      - July 1961-June 1962. (Box 3)
      - July 1962-June 1963. (Box 3)
      - July 1963-June 1964. (Box 3)
      - July 1964-June 1966. (Box 3)
      - July 1966-June 1967. (Box 3)
      - July 1967-June 1971. (Box 3)
      - July 1971-June 1975. (Box 3)
      - July 1975-February 1977. (Box 4)
      - April 1977-June 1978. (Box 4)
    - Loose Minutes.
      - 1955. (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - 1956. (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - 1956-1957. (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - 1972. (Box 9, Folder 4)
      - 1973. (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - 1974. (Box 9, Folder 6)
      - 1975. (Box 9, Folder 7)
      - 1976. (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - January-June 1977. (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - July-December 1977. (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - 1978. (Box 10, Folder 4)
      - July 1978-March 1981 (folder 1 of 3). (Box 10, Folder 5)
      - July 1978-March 1981 (folder 2 of 3). (Box 10, Folder 6)
      - July 1978-March 1981 (folder 3 of 3). (Box 10, Folder 7)
      - January-July 1979. (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - September 1979. (Box 11, Folder 2)
      - October-December 1979. (Box 11, Folder 3)
      - January-June 1980. (Box 11, Folder 4)
      - July-October 1980. (Box 11, Folder 5)
      - December 1980. (Box 11, Folder 6)
      - January-March 1981. (Box 11, Folder 7)
      - April-May 1981. (Box 11, Folder 8)
      - June-October 1981. (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - November-December 1981. (Box 12, Folder 2)
      - January-April 1982. (Box 12, Folder 3)
      - May-September 1982. (Box 12, Folder 4)
      - October-December 1982. (Box 12, Folder 5)
      - January-February 1983. (Box 12, Folder 6)
      - March-June 1983. (Box 12, Folder 7)
      - July-September 1983. (Box 12, Folder 8)
      - October-December 1983. (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - January-March 1984. (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - April-May 1984. (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - June 1984. (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - August-December 1984. (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - January-March 1985. (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - April-June 1985. (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - August 1985. (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - September 1985. (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - October-November 1985. (Box 14, Folder 2)
      - December 1985. (Box 14, Folder 3)
      - January-February 1986. (Box 14, Folder 4)
      - March-April 1986. (Box 14, Folder 5)
      - May-June 1986. (Box 14, Folder 6)
      - August-September 1986. (Box 14, Folder 7)
      - October-December 1986. (Box 14, Folder 8)
      - January-May 1987. (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - June 1987. (Box 15, Folder 2)
      - June 1987. (Box 15, Folder 3)
      - August-October 1987. (Box 15, Folder 4)
      - November-December 1987. (Box 15, Folder 5)
      - January-June 1988. (Box 15, Folder 6)
      - August-December 1988. (Box 15, Folder 7)
      - January-April 1989. (Box 15, Folder 8)
      - May-June 1989. (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - August-September 1989. (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - October-December 1989. (Box 16, Folder 3)
      - January-February 1990. (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - March-May 1990. (Box 16, Folder 5)
      - August-December 1990. (Box 16, Folder 6)
      - January-March 1991. (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - April-June 1991. (Box 16, Folder 8)
      - July-December 1991. (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - January-March 1992. (Box 17, Folder 2)
      - April-June 1992. (Box 17, Folder 3)
      - July-December 1992. (Box 17, Folder 4)
      - January-June 1993. (Box 17, Folder 5)
      - July-November 1993. (Box 17, Folder 6)
      - January-June 1994. (Box 17, Folder 7)
      - July-December 1994. (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - January-June 1995. (Box 18, Folder 2)
      - July-November 1995. (Box 18, Folder 3)
      - February-June 1996. (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Subseries B. Minutes, Executive Sessions, 1948-1979. (Box 4, 5, 18.)
    Contains the minutes of the executive session meetings of the State Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services Board. Some of the minutes exist in two forms, bound and loose. The bound minutes are in straight chronological order, but many of the loose and more recent minutes are arranged in reverse chronological order. The minutes include more specific and detailed information than the regular session minutes and tend to delve more deeply into personnel and patient issues.
    - Bound Minutes.
      - September 1948-June 1952. (Box 4)
      - July 1952-June 1954. (Box 4)
      - July 1954-June 1956. (Box 4)
      - July 1956-June 1958. (Box 4)
      - July 1958-June 1959. (Box 4)
      - July 1959-June 1960. (Box 4)
      - July 1960-June 1961. (Box 4)
      - July 1961-June 1962. (Box 4)
      - July 1962-June 1963. (Box 4)
      - July 1963-June 1964. (Box 4)
      - July 1964-June 1966. (Box 5)
      - July 1966-June 1967. (Box 5)
      - July 1967-June 1971. (Box 5)
      - July 1971-March 1979. (Box 5)
    - Loose Minutes.
      - 1972-1974. (Box 18, Folder 5)
      - 1975-1976. (Box 18, Folder 6)
      - 1977-1980. (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Subseries C. Minutes, Other, 1965-1993. (Box 18-19.)
    Restricted: Meeting minutes containing patient names and information that are less than 75 years old. These records may require review by an archivist and/or redaction (if it is possible) before they are served. Contains several folders of minutes created by other committees associated with the Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services Board, including the Professional Advisory Board which produced reports and recommendations to the Department on issues such as community programs, professionalism and deinstitutionalization. Other minutes cover the meetings of various standing committees such as the Policy Committee, Planning and Budget Committee, and the Joint Board Liasion Committee which joined together the Board of Health, Board of Education, Board of Social Services and the Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services Board.
    Arranged alphabetically.
    - Professional Advisory Board, 1972-1976. (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Regarding Title IV of the Civil Rights Act, 1965-1969. (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - Standing Committees: Evaluation Committee, 1982-1985. (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Standing Committees: Joint Liasion Committee, 1985-1987. (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Standing Committees: Joint Liaison Committee, 1988-1989. (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Standing Committees: Joint Liaison Committee, 1990-1991. (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Standing Committees: Joint Liasion Committee, 1992-1993. (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Standing Committees: Planning and Budget Committee, 1982-1984. (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Standing Committees: Policy Committee, 1982-1984. (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Subseries D. Indices to Minutes, 1948-1980. (Box 5, 19, 20.)
    Contains bound and loose paper indices for the minutes of the State Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services Board, as well as its earlier incarnations. The indices provide page numbers that correspond with particular topics found within the minutes.
    Arranged with bound indices first and loose indices second, and then chronologically within.
    - Bound Indices.
      - July 1948-June 1967. (Box 5)
      - July 1967-December 1980. (Box 5)
    - Loose Indices.
      - 1968-1971. (Box 19, Folder 8)
      - 1972-1974. (Box 19, Folder 9)
      - 1975-1976. (Box 19, Folder 10)
      - 1977-1978. (Box 19, Folder 11)
      - 1979-1980. (Box 19, Folder 12)
      - 1981-1986. (Box 20, Folder 1)
      - 1987-1993. (Box 20, Folder 2)
- Series II. Minutes, Special Board of Directors of the State Colony for Epileptics and Feebleminded, 1910-1937. (Box 6.)
  Restricted: Meeting minutes containing patient names and information that are less than 75 years old. These records may require review by an archivist and/or redaction (if it is possible) before they are served. Contains four volumes of bound meeting minutes of the Special Board of Directors of the State Colony for Epileptics and Feebleminded. The earlier name for the Board was the Special Board of Directors of the State Colony for Epileptics, which was changed to include "feebleminded" in 1920. The Special Board dealt only with issues specific to the Colony. The earliest minutes are handwritten and the later minutes are typed. The minutes include information on personnel, budgetary, operational, and patient issues specific to the State Colony.
  - March 1910 - September 1914. (Box 6)
  - October 1914 - October 1920. (Box 6)
  - November 1920 - June 1925. (Box 6)
  - July 1925 - June 1937. (Box 6)
- Series III. Minutes, Miscellaneous Organizations, 1915-1922. (Box 6.)
  Contains one volume of bound minutes for three local mental health organizations. The Virginia Social Hygiene Association was formed in 1915 with the purpose of fighting social evils and vice. The Virginia Society for Mental Hygiene was founded in 1917 with the goal of improving care for mentally ill patients and the prevention of mental deficiency. The Mental Health Commission was appointed by the Governor by an act of the General Assembly in 1922. The Commission was charged with studying a variety of mental health issues affecting the citizens of Virginia. Deliniations between the sets of minutes are not clearly marked.
  Arrangement below reflects arrangement in the volume (loosely chronological).
  - Virginia Social Hygiene Association, 1915-1922. (Box 6)
  - Virginia Society for Mental Hygiene, 1917. (Box 6)
  - Mental Health Commission, 1922. (Box 6)
- Series IV. Chronological Files, 1981-1994. (Box 20-24.)
  Restricted: Files and documents containing patient names and information that are less than 75 years old. These records may require review by an archivist and/or redaction (if it is possible) before they are served. Contains files comprised of memorandums and other correspondence associated with particular individuals or entities over a period of time. The files include correspondence to and from the Board of Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services, as well as individuals within the department, regarding many types of business and hospital-related issues. The records were found in several separate packets and were retained together. As a result, there are many instances of overlapping dates that are not explained.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1981-1982. (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - 1981-1982. (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - 1982-1983. (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - 1982-1983. (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - 1982-1983. (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - July 1983-June 1984. (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - July 1983-May 1984. (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - November 1983 - June 1984. (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - November 1983-June 1984. (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - 1984-1985. (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - 1984-1985. (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - 1985. (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - 1985. (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - 1985. (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - 1986. (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - 1986. (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - May 1987-March 1988. (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - June-November 1987. (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - October 1987-June 1989. (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - October 1987-June 1989. (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - October 1987-June 1989. (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - October 1987-June 1989. (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - October 1987-June 1989. (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - November 1987-June 1988. (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - November 1987-June 1988. (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - July 1989-June 1990. (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - July 1989-June 1990. (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - July 1989-June 1990. (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - July 1989-June 1990. (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - July 1990-June 1991. (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - July 1990-June 1991. (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - July 1990-June 1991. (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - July 1991-June 1992. (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - July 1991-June 1992. (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - July 1992-June 1993. (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - July 1992-June 1993. (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - July 1993-June 1994. (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - July 1993-June 1994. (Box 24, Folder 7)
- Series V. Mental Hygiene Surveys, 1938-1947. (Box 6-7.)
  Restricted: Surveys containing patient names and information that are less than 75 years old. These records may require review by an archivist and/or redaction (if it is possible) before they are served. Contains six bound volumes of monthly surveys or reports compiled by the State Hospital Board. The surveys contain financial and operational information, reports and editorials from agency and department officials, patient and hospital statistical information, as well as news and notes from individual institutions.
  - January-June 1938. (Box 6)
  - July 1938-June 1939. (Box 6)
  - August 1940-June 1941. (Box 6)
  - July 1941-June 1942. (Box 7)
  - July 1945-June 1946. (Box 7)
  - June 1946-July 1947. (Box 7)
- Series VI. Reports and Manuals, 1943-1972. (Box 7-8.)
  Restricted: Investigation records containing patient names and information that are less than 75 years old. These records may require review by an archivist and/or redaction (if it is possible) before they are served. Contains several volumes devoted to investigations of Eastern and Western State Hospitals conducted by the State Hospital Board in 1943. The investigations focused on the conditions and methods of operation at the hospitals. Included here are hearing transcripts, testimonies and other material compiled by the Board, as well as a copy of the final report. In addition to the investigation volumes, there are also two more general reports on state mental health facilities and a policies and procedures manual.
  - Hearings, Eastern State Hospital, 1943. (Box 7)
  - Letters and Data Concerning Investigation by the State Hospital Board of the Eastern State Hospital, 1943. (Box 7)
  - Letters and Data Concerning Investigation by the State Hospital Board of the Western State Hospital, 1943. (Box 7)
  - Report of the State Hospital Board to the Governor Concerning Investigation of the Eastern and Western State Hospitals, 1943. (Box 7)
  - Report on the Department of Mental Hygiene and Hospitals and the Mental Institutions, 1949 [2 copies]. (Box 8)
  - Report on the State Mental Hospitals of Virginia Made by the Central Inspection Board of the American Psychiatric Association, 1950 [2 final copies and 3 draft copies]. (Box 8)
  - Manual of Standard Administrative Practices and Procedures, 1966-1972. (Box 8)